<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Marca1>
  <Root>
    <titulo_cap_texto>Best friends forever</titulo_cap_texto>





    <imagem></imagem>
    <p class="img-subtitle">Friends sharing a moment together.</p>
    <credito>FG Trade/iStockphoto.com</credito>
    <p class="general-text">
      Do you prefer one hundred
      <i>reais</i>
      in your wallet or a hundred friends in life? In Spain, according to an old saying, “With the money ending, the friendship ends”, while, in Russia, there is another adage: “Instead of having one hundred rubles, it is better to have one hundred friends.”
    </p>
    <p class="general-text">Americans use the word “friend” in a very general way, both for casual acquaintances and close friends, and friendship is subject to changes in intensity as people move, change jobs, marry or discover new interests. Yet, in China, the word “pengyou” (friend) is used only to refer to a person who is known and trusted by the speaker for several years. Still, in all countries, sharing experiences is usually the basis for making a friend. </p>
    <p class="general-text">Friendships are meaningful anywhere, and, for teens, especially, it’s important to feel a sense of belonging and acceptance by their peers. Having a network of friends, supporting family and caring teachers may help students avoid negative relationships, such as the abusive behavior of bullies. Learning positive friendship skills can be socially helpful and make teenagers feel happier and more conﬁdent.</p>



    <li>Do you think there are particular characteristics of friendship in Brazil, like the ones described in the text?</li>
    <li>There is a saying “To have a good friend, you need to be a good friend.” How can you be a good friend?</li>
    <li>What qualities are good in a friend? Do you consider the members of your family good friends?</li>
   
   
    <boxe_02_texto>




      Neste capítulo, serão abordadas as habilidades
      <boxe_06_texto>EM13LGG301,</boxe_06_texto>
      ,
      <boxe_06_texto>EM13LGG402</boxe_06_texto>
      ,
      <boxe_06_texto>EM13LGG403</boxe_06_texto>
      .
    </boxe_02_texto>
    <p class="general-text">
      <secao_03>
        Dive in
        <titulo1>Verbs: what they are, how to use them</titulo1>
        <secao_texto>
          A verb is a word that expresses an action or a state of being. It can be considered as one of the most important parts of a sentence, and it is for sure the most important part of the predicate, as you have learned in Portuguese. There are also the
          <b>helping</b>
          or
          <b>auxiliary verbs</b>
          , that help the action or linking verbs (an auxiliary verb + a verb is called a
          <b>verb phrase</b>
          ).
          <b></b>
        </secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>Look at the following sentences and underline the verbs in them.</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>One easy way to help you recognize a verb is looking at its location compared to the subject. Verbs usually come after a noun or pronoun. These nouns and pronouns are referred to as the subject of the sentence. </secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>Check the example:</secao_texto>


        <secao_texto>The verb “thought” comes after the noun “Jack”, so the action Jack (subject) was performing was “thinking” (verb).</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>There are more than ten different types of verbs that are grouped together by function. Take a look at five of </secao_texto>
        <secao_texto></secao_texto>
        <secao_texto></secao_texto>
        <secao_texto></secao_texto>
        <secao_texto></secao_texto>
        <secao_texto></secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>the most common ones.</secao_texto>
        <secao_02_titulo1>Grammaring</secao_02_titulo1>
        <secao_texto>Based on what you have learned about verbs, answer the following questions.</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto></secao_texto>
        <secao_exercicio_numerador>1	</secao_exercicio_numerador>
        Read the excerpt and underline the verbs.
        <secao_texto_citado>Everyone can use a friend or two. Having a few friends is great, but having a best friend is even better. From wacky adventures to great memories, a best friend can always find a way to magically put a smile on your face. Best friends are the people we deeply trust, the ones who we laugh with, cry to, and tell our deepest and darkest secrets to.</secao_texto_citado>
        <fonte>
          KRICKET, Kate. “Best friend quotes”.
          <i>Luvze</i>
          , 24 set. 2016. Available at www.luvze.com/best-friend-quotes. Accessed on June 23rd, 2021.
        </fonte>
        <secao_exercicio_numerador>2	</secao_exercicio_numerador>
        Read the sentences and indicate the function of each verb in bold.
        <item_lista>
          <b>a)	</b>
          It hasn’t
          <b>rained</b>
          all this month.
        </item_lista>
        <item_lista>
          <b>b)	</b>
          What
          <b>does</b>
          Maria like to drink?
        </item_lista>
        <item_lista>
          <b>c)	</b>
          You
          <b>are</b>
          my sunshine.
        </item_lista>
        <item_lista>
          <b>d)	</b>
          Does Peter
          <b>believe</b>
          in miracles?
        </item_lista>
        <item_lista>
          <b>e)	</b>
          If you want to pass the exams, you
          <b>must</b>
          study harder.
        </item_lista>
        <secao_texto></secao_texto>
        <secao_exercicio_numerador>3	</secao_exercicio_numerador>
        Where can verbs go in a sentence? Use the verbs in the chart to fill in the blanks correctly. Attention: some words can be repeated.
        <secao_02_titulo1></secao_02_titulo1>
        <secao_02_titulo1></secao_02_titulo1>
        <secao_texto>
          <b>
            <Glossario>
              <boxe_01_texto>bound – spare – resting – was – said – free – parted – repay – lay – stalking – roused – let – filled – get – think – came – caught – go – will – running – help – struggling – laid – gnawed – begged – unable – kill – knew – laughed – ran – could – repay – found – would – can</boxe_01_texto>
            </Glossario>
          </b>
        </secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>
          <b>The Lion &amp; the Mouse</b>
        </secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>A Lion  asleep in the forest, his great head  on his paws. A timid little Mouse  upon him unexpectedly, and in her fright and haste to  away,  across the Lion’s nose.  from his nap, the Lion  his huge paw angrily on the tiny creature to  her.</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>“ me!”  the poor Mouse. “Please  me  and some day I  surely  you.”</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>The Lion  much amused to  that a Mouse  ever  him. But he   generous and finally  the Mouse .</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>Some days later, while  his prey in the forest, the Lion   in the toils of a hunter’s net.  to  himself, he  the forest with his angry roaring. The Mouse  the voice and quickly  the Lion  in the net.</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto> to one of the great ropes that  him, she  it until it  and soon the Lion  free.</secao_texto>
        <secao_texto>“You  when I  I    you,”  the Mouse. “Now you    that even a Mouse   a Lion.”</secao_texto>
        <fonte>
          AESOP. “The Lion &amp; the Mouse”.
          <i> The Aesop for Children</i>
          . Chicago: Rand, McNally &amp; Co., c. 1919.
        </fonte>
        Find in the next text one example of each type of verb and write them down.
        <item_lista>Main verbs or action verbs:</item_lista>
        <item_lista>Linking verbs or stative verbs: </item_lista>
        <item_lista>Auxiliary verbs or helping verbs: </item_lista>
        <item_lista>Modal verbs:</item_lista>
        <item_lista>The verb to be:</item_lista>
        <p class="general-text">Now, let’s read the text.</p>
        <secao_texto_citado>[...] </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>Adult friendships can be tricky. They’re not as fragile as the friendships of the teenage years, when something as simple as your pal going to Starbucks with someone else can shake your relationship to its foundations; but neither is it like primary school, where you can just go up to someone in the playground and decide you are now best friends for ever. [...]</secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>[...] I’ve had the same group of friends for more than half my life – one from the first year of secondary school, when we bonded over whatever it is 11-year-olds bond over, and two I met a couple of years later, during an intense emo phase. We have all evolved from being teenagers who listened to My Chemical Romance on our Sony Ericssons in the park to adults with jobs and, for one of us, a baby. It’s lucky that we still like each other, but that doesn’t mean there was no work involved. Here are some of the things I’ve learned about making those connections last. [...]</secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>
          <b>[...]  Nostalgia is overrated</b>
        </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>Remember that weird haircut you got? Or that time you peed yourself when you were kind of too old to be peeing yourself? Or when you went through a phase where you lied and told everyone your name was Scarlet because you wanted to seem more interesting? If you start every conversation with, “Hey, remember that time when...?” you and your friend will die of boredom. [...] </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>
          <b>[...] ... but it’s good to have “your thing”</b>
        </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>People get busy and life has dramatic ups and downs, but if you watch Drag Race every Friday together or bake Betty Crocker cookies every month, before eating most of the dough because, honestly, it’s better than the final product, you have something to anchor you through the chaos of life.</secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>
          <b>[...] The only way to fight is like siblings</b>
        </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>As teenagers, a friend and I got into a really vicious fight: long story short, I hit her on the arm with a loaf of bread and it ended with her storming out of the front door.</secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>Ultimately, she returned with a pint of milk, we made some tea and the fight was over. Because unless something truly terrible happens, there’s no room for grudges. You will annoy each other, of course, but it’s always better to get over it quickly. You also love each other and probably aren’t going to end a friendship because one of you said a dress in Topshop was something the ghost of a Victorian child would wear, not realizing</secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>the other one had the same dress at home.</secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>
          <b>Real friends don’t cancel plans</b>
        </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>We’ve reached peak “I love cancelled plans!” culture. Every fast-fashion line carries at least one “Tacos. Netflix. Cancelled Plans. YASSS” T-shirt. And yes, it can feel great to cancel on things you were dreading, and for some it is an important part of maintaining good mental health. But with the exception of that, making a cutesy introversion meme your mantra is no way to live your life.</secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>Commitment is key to maintaining real relationships. I’m sure that my friends didn’t actively enjoy the times they came over to see me knowing I was just going to cry because I was too sad to talk, but they turned up, because they know I would do the same for them. [...] </secao_texto_citado>
        <fonte>NAHAR, Jasmin. The Guardian, 27 abr. 2019. © Copyright Guardian News &amp; Media Ltd, 2019.</fonte>
        Choose the alternative that contains the best possible title for the article.
        <item_lista>How to be best friends forever: don’t cancel, fight like siblings and make new memories.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>The secret to make friends during early years at school: have many cute moments.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>How to create a large circle of friends when you reach adulthood: show some respect.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>Choose your friends carefully.</item_lista>
        Write T (true) or F (false) for the sentences, according to the information from the text. Correct the false sentences.
        <b>(   ) </b>
        Having friends as an adult is as simple as making friends as a child.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        Jasmin Nahar believes maintaining friends from when you were younger is easy, but it also requires a lot of luck.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        Being very nostalgic is not good for long lasting friendship.
        <b>   )	 </b>
        If you want to have a long term friendship you must let go the stupid fights and make peace soon.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        Real friends cancel plans when they discover you are sad and in no mood for happiness.The following words are underlined in the text. Match them to their correct definitions (taken from: https://en.oxforddictionaries.com).
        <item_lista>overrated </item_lista>
        <item_lista>boredom </item_lista>
        <item_lista>anchor</item_lista>
        <item_lista>siblings</item_lista>
        <item_lista>annoy</item_lista>
        <item_lista>commitment</item_lista>
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        verb – Provide with a firm basis or foundation.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        noun – The state or quality of being dedicated to a cause, activity etc.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        adjective – Have a higher opinion of (someone or something) than is deserved.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        verb – Make (someone) a little angry; irritate.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        noun – The state of being weary and restless through lack of interest.
        <b>(   )	 </b>
        noun – Each of two or more children or offspring
        <secao_02>
          <boxe_01_titulo1>Speak out</boxe_01_titulo1>
          <boxe_03_texto></boxe_03_texto>
          <boxe_03_titulo1>Can friendship prevent diseases?</boxe_03_titulo1>
          <boxe_03_texto>Not only older people benefit form friendship, people of all ages do. With good friends, we can drop our masks and be imperfect, without judgement. This lowers stress level, improves the immune system, the attentional focus, as well as the physical and mental performance. </boxe_03_texto>
          <boxe_03_texto>In pairs, try to find an explanation for why people with fewer or no friends tend to become sick easier.</boxe_03_texto>
        </secao_02>
      </secao_03>
    </p>
    <p class="general-text">
      <boxe_02>
        practice it!
        <secao_texto>
          <b>EsPCEx-SP 2017 </b>
          Leia o texto e responda às questões 1, 2 e 3.
        </secao_texto>
        <secao_titulo_citado>Military operations in megacities</secao_titulo_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>
          <b>A linguistic perspective</b>
        </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>The challenge of conducting future military operations within megacities (cities with populations over ten million) lies in understanding the dynamic and multidimensional complexities of these urban areas. Military operations in megacities, whether combat-oriented or otherwise, will be similar to those </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>in other urban environments, but will be complicated by factors unique to the megacity environment. </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>First and foremost, megacities are largely multilingual. While this can be said of large cities in general, the scale of multilingualism in megacities magnifies its effects. For instance, in New York City (NYC) – a metropolitan megacity of over eighteen million people – nine foreign languages are spoken by communities of one hundred thousand or larger. Language also plays a role in determining one’s identity and the language community in which one decides to live. For example, the majority of Russian speakers in NYC tend to live in south Brooklyn and Staten Island, while Chinese speakers tend to cluster in Manhattan and Sunset Park. In megacities, language, culture, and regional context go hand in hand and often reach beyond ethnic identities. </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>In order to fully understand the context of a megacity, we must understand the role of the languages used in its communities. How (1) language communities interact in megacities? What tensions (2) caused by multiple language communities in urban space? What role (3) language play in the power structures (government or otherwise) of megacities?</secao_texto_citado>
        <fonte>
          Adapted from
          <i>Military Review</i>
          – Jan/Feb 2016.
        </fonte>
        Choose the statement in which the word lies is used with the same meaning as in paragraph 1.
        <item_lista>He lies in the sun for too long. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>His skill lies in his ability to communicate. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>I can tell from her face that she lies. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>A giant crocodile lies in wait for its prey. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>This item always lies over for a next meeting.</item_lista>
        Choose the alternative containing the correct words to respectively complete gaps (1), (2) and (3) in paragraph 3.
        <item_lista>is, does, do </item_lista>
        <item_lista>do, are, do </item_lista>
        <item_lista>are, is, do </item_lista>
        <item_lista>are, do, does </item_lista>
        <item_lista>do, are, does </item_lista>
        According to the text, choose the correct statement.
        <item_lista>Urban environments are more complex than megacities. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>Nine languages are spoken in large cities. </item_lista>
        <fonte>(http://etxerox.blogspot.com.br)</fonte>
        <item_lista>Language is of great concern to the military. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>Ethnic identities are limited by regional context. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>Military operations are just combat-oriented.</item_lista>
        <secao_exercicio>
          <b>Unifesp 2018 </b>
          Texto para as questões de 4 a 6.
        </secao_exercicio>
        Os quadrinhos têm como tema principal
        <item_lista>o uso excessivo de mídias sociais pelos adolescentes. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>a falta de controle dos filhos pelos pais. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>o compartilhamento de brinquedos e equipamentos domésticos pelas crianças. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>a denúncia do relacionamento conflituoso entre irmãos adolescentes. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>a diferença de necessidade de comunicação de meninas e meninos. </item_lista>
        A lacuna numerada no quarto quadrinho deve ser preenchida por
        <item_lista>is writing. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>have written. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>used to write. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>might write. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>could have written. </item_lista>
        The word “loopy” can be replaced, with no meaning change, by
        <item_lista>affectionate.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>obsessed.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>upbeat.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>selfish.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>spoilt.</item_lista>
        <p class="general-text"></p>
        <secao_texto>
          <b>UPF-RS 2015 </b>
          Read the text and answer the questions 7 to 9.
        </secao_texto>
        <p class="general-text"></p>
        <secao_titulo_citado>Bag your Bags, Bring ’em Back</secao_titulo_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>The best way to recycle your plastic bags and film is to bring them back to a store that collects them for recycling. Just stuff them clean and dry into a single plastic bag, tie it up, and drop it into a plastic bag collection container found at the retail partners. Note: The stores listed below have partnered with King County to promote the Bag Your Bag campaign. There may be other stores not listed that accept plastic bags for recycling. </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>Plastic bags and film collected at grocery stores stay cleaner and are easier for recycling facilities to process than bags placed in your home recycling collection bin. The bags are turned into new products like decking, benches, playground structures, and new plastic bags. And remember to bring along your reusable bags when you shop. </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>The Bag your Bags, Bring ’em Back campaign is a partnership between the King County Solid Waste Division and local grocery stores to show the best way to recycle plastic bags. </secao_texto_citado>
        <fonte>(Retrieved and adapted from http://your.kingcounty.gov/solidwaste/garbage-recycling/bag-your-bags.asp. Access on September 28th, 2014).</fonte>
        Considering the fragment “Plastic bags and film collected at grocery stores stay cleaner and are easier for recycling facilities to process than bags placed in your home recycling collection bin” (
        <b>lines 10 to 13</b>
        ), the alternative in which there is no change in meaning is:
        <item_lista>Bags placed in your home recycling collection bin stay dirtier and are more difficult for recycling facilities to process than plastic bags and film collected at grocery stores.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>Bags placed in your home recycling collection bin stay as clean and are easy for recycling facilities to process as plastic bags and film collected at grocery stores.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>Bags placed in your home recycling collection bin stay cleaner and are easier for recycling facilities to process than plastic bags and film collected at grocery stores.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>Bags placed in your home recycling collection bin are the cleanest and the easiest ones for recycling facilities to process.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>Bags placed in your home recycling collection bin do not stay dirtier and are not more difficult for recycling facilities to process than plastic bags and film collected at grocery stores. </item_lista>
        Traditionally, at a grocery store, you can buy
        <item_lista>shoes.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>clothes.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>food.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>medicines.</item_lista>
        <item_lista>electronics.</item_lista>
        In the title of the campaign, “
        <b>Bag</b>
        your
        <b>Bags</b>
        , Bring ’em Back”, the words in bold are respectively classified as:
        <item_lista>verb and noun. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>verb and adjective. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>noun and verb. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>noun and adjective. </item_lista>
        <item_lista>adjective and verb.</item_lista>
        <b>Eear-SP 2019</b>
        Read the text and complete the blanks with the appropriate verbs.
        <secao_texto_citado>Dear John, </secao_texto_citado>
        <secao_texto_citado>How are you? Here I am in Mayflower in an English class with my cousin. Here in Mayflower the students __________ to school in the morning, but in Brazil __________ the option to study during the morning or after lunch. I think this option </secao_texto_citado>
      </boxe_02>
    </p>
  </Root>
</Marca1>